chapter 48 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is In the public domain Black
Beauty by Anna Su chapter 48 Farmer Thor good and His Grandson
Willie At this sale, of course I found myself in company with the old broken
down horses— —some lame, some broken winded some old, and some that I am sure it
would have been merciful to shoot.
The buyers and sellers, too, many of them, looked not much better off than the poor
beasts they were bargaining about. There were poor old men, trying to get a horse
or a pony for a few pounds, that might drag about some little wood or coal
cart. There were poor men trying to sell a worn out beast for two or3 rather than
have the greater loss of killing him. Some of them looked as if poverty
and hard times had hardened them all over; but there were others that I would
have willingly used the last of my strength in serving; poor and shabby, but
kind and human, with voices that I could trust. There was one tottering old man
who took a great fancy to me, and I to
him, but I was not strong enough— —it was an anxious
time! Coming from the better part of the fair, I noticed a man who looked like a
gentleman farmer, with a young boy by his side; he had a broad back and round
shoulders, a kind, ruddy face, and he wor a broad brimmed
hat. When he came up to me and my companions he stood still and gave a
pitiful look round upon us. I saw his eye
rest on me; I still had a good mane and tail, which did something for my
appearance. I pricked my ears and looked at him. “There's a horse, Willie, that has
known better days.” “Poor old fellow!” said the boy, “do you think grandpaa he was
ever a carriage horse?” “Oh, yes! my boy,” said the farmer, coming closer, “he might have been
anything when he was young; look at his nostrils and his ears, the shape of his
neck and shoulder; there's a deal of breeding about that
horse.” He put out his hand and gave me a
kind pat on the neck. I put out my nose in answer to his kindness; the boy
stroked my face. “Poor old fellow! see, grandpapa, how well he understands kindness. Could not
you buy him and make him young again as you did with
Ladybird?” “My dear boy, I can't make all old horses young; besides, Ladybird was
not so very old, as she was run down and badly used.” “Well, grandpapa, I don't believe that
this one is old; look at his man and tail.
I wish you would look into his mouth, and then you could tell; though he's so very
thin, his eyes are not sunk like some old horses'.” The old gentleman laughed. “Bless
the boy! he is as horsey as his old grandfather.” “But do look at his mouth,
grandpapa, and ask the price I'm sure he would grow young in our
meadows.” The man who had brought me for sale now put in his word. “The young
gentleman's a real knowing on sir. Now the fact is, this ear hor is just pulled
down with overwork in the cabs; he's not an old one, and I hear as how the
veterinary should say, that a six months runoff should set him right up, being as
how his wind was not broken. I've had the tending of him these 10 days past, and a
grateful pleasanter animal I never never met with, and it would be worth a
gentleman's while to give a5 note for him, and let him have a chance. I'll be
bound he'd be worth 20 next spring.” The old gentleman laughed, and the
little boy looked up eagerly. “Oh, grandpapa, did you not say the cult sold
for5 more than you expected? You would not be poorer if you did buy this one.”
The farmer slowly felt my legs, which were much swelled and strained; then he
looked at my mouth 13 or 14 I should say; just trot him out, will
you?” I arched my poor thin neck, raised my tail a little, and threw out my legs as
well as I could, for they were very stiff. “What is the lowest you will take
for him?” said the farmer as I came back £5 sir; that was the lowest price my master
set it is a speculation,” said the old gentleman, shaking his head, but at the
same time slowly drawing out his purse, “quite a speculation! Have you any more
business here?” he said, counting the sovereigns into his
hand. “No, sir, I can take him for you to the inn, if you
please.” “Do so, I now going there.” They walked forward, and I was led
behind. The boy could hardly control his delight, and the old gentleman seemed to enjoy his
pleasure. I had a good feed at the inn, and was then gently ridden home by a
servant of my new master's, and turned into a large meadow with a shed in one corner of
it. Mr Thor good for that was the name of my benefactor, gave orders that I should
have hay and oats every night and morning, and the run of the meadow during
the day, and, “you, Willie,” said he, “must take the oversight of him; I give him in
charge to you.” The boy was proud of his charge, and undertook it in all
seriousness. There was not a day when he did not pay me a visit some times
picking me out from among the other horses, and giving me a bit of carrot, or
something good, or sometimes standing by me while I ate my
oats. He always came with kind words and caresses, and of course I grew very fond
of him. He called me Old Crony, as I used
to come to him in the field and follow him about. Sometimes he brought his
grandfather, who always looked closely at my legs. “This is our point, Willie,” he would
say; “but he is improving so steadily that I think we shall see a change for the
better in the spring.” The perfect rest, the good food, the soft turf, and gentle exercise, soon
began to tell on my condition and my spirits. I had a good constitution from
my mother, and I was never strained when I was young, so that I had a better
chance than many horses who have been worked before they came to their full
strength. During the winter my legs improved so much that I began to feel quite young again
a spring came round, and one day in March Mr Thor good determined that he would
try me in the fighton I was well pleased, and he and
Willie drove me a few miles. My legs were not stiff now, and I did the work with
perfect ease. “He's growing young, Willie; we must give him a little gentle work now, and by
Midsummer he will be as good as Ladybird.
He has a beautiful mouth and good paces; they can't be
better.” “Oh grandpaa how how glad I am you
brought him!” “So am I, my boy; but he has to
thank you more than me; we must now be looking out for a quiet Gentile place
for him, where he will be valued end of chapter